Daniel Zarate

Prosper, TX 75078 • 469-258-5424 • <u>daniel@zarate.org</u> <u>linkedin.com/in/daniel-zarate-532b28a3</u> • <u>danielzarate.myportfolio.com</u> • <u>github.com/dzarate999</u>

IT Project / Product Management

Versatile career history with a 12-year track record of innovation and success

Notable project management specialist with a successful background in executing marketing plans, business initiatives, and product deliverables towards significant revenue and profit growth. Demonstrate proven skills and knowledge in maintaining optimal workplace practices emphasizing ongoing workflow improvement and market expansion. Possess additional IT-focused talents encompassing technical support and troubleshooting, as well as previous experiences as graphic designer and web development/network administration specialist. *Core competencies include:*

- Project Management & Estimation
- Inventory Management
- Business Development
- Organizational Design & Planning
- Regulatory Compliance
- Customer Relationship Management
- Technical Support & Troubleshooting
- Teambuilding & Leadership

Professional Experience

First Signs Graphic Solutions, Lewisville, TX

Project Manager / Project Estimator / Business Development Manager, 1/2019 - 4/2019, Present (as consultant)

Maintained overall project management efforts via hands-on brainstorming, consulting, surveying, solution design, production, and installation while also providing accurate cost estimations and takeoffs to help quantify all job-related components. Supported additional product management by coordinating all planning, forecasting, marketing, and production phases, and satisfied established corporate goals by designing detailed graphics in conjunction with various clients. Ensured regulatory compliance in adherence to necessary permitting and legal requirements across differing cities. Redirected companywide focus—and devised appropriate tactics—to successfully capture business in previously untapped commercial construction markets.

- Reduced the company's reliance on external resources by participating in the complete development of a five-year business plan.
- Boosted collaboration via the synchronization of overall workflow and redefinition of job descriptions;
 similarly boosted efficiency levels via the streamlining and standardization of client ordering processes.
- Secured new accounts and business opportunities by actively networking with potential clients including over \$25K in job bids on behalf of the DFW International Airport.

D&R Signs Dallas, Frisco, TX

Project Manager / Project Estimator / Account Manager / Operations Manager, 1/2015 - 1/2019

Administered 30+ simultaneous residential homebuilders/developers and marketing agency projects in one of the largest housing market expansions in the United States. Oversaw all project management phases with direct accountability for estimates, graphic design, production, installation, and permits. Enabled local network operations by configuring all company computers and industrial printers while also terminating and establishing networking cables throughout the office. Facilitated daily operations by building all company computers and installing crucial software applications, and accommodated challenging economical and practical situations via strategic and innovative solutions. Identified and secured new clients within the greater Dallas/Fort Worth area through dedicated market research.

Daniel Zarate

Page 2 of 2

- Founded D&R Signs Dallas from the ground up as a privately owned company operating from a personal
 residence, eventually growing it to a full-fledged business with multiple employees and attracting business
 away from three leading competitors despite lower name recognition and client base.
- Earned the majority of regional market shares for homebuilder accounts within the span of four years;
 similarly earned \$2M in annual revenue by increasing D&R's client base from zero to 50 within four years.
- Created a Microsoft Access-based system to properly catalogue growing and unwieldy inventory into balanced and easily searchable sections.
- Received multiple award nominations for the company's signage, and had another sign featured on the Barstool Sports blog.

Dallas Police Department, Dallas, TX

Police Officer, 1/2007 - 1/2015

Utilized proper conflict resolution to mediate tense or hostile situations in a calm and diplomatic manner, and leveraged trusted communication and listening skills to interact with the general public and coworkers. Investigated suspicious and criminal activity while also reporting offenses, making arrests, and testifying in court. Maintained compliance with necessary procedures, provided precise and detailed documentation, and cultivated positive connections with residents and business owners within the assigned territory.

- Awarded "Officer of the Quarter" in 2013 for outstanding job performance.
- Consistently reduced crime rates in each assigned sector while also earning recognition as the "go-to" officer for research into suspects' probable locations, contacts, and hideouts.

Technical Proficiencies

Platforms: Windows, Mac OS, Android iOS

Tools: MS Office Suite (Word/Excel/PowerPoint/Outlook/Access), Adobe Creative Cloud

(Photoshop/Acrobat/Premiere Pro/After Effects/InDesign/Lightroom/Illustrator), Unity, HTML, CSS,

JavaScript, ReactJS, NodeJS, MongoDB, APIs

Education and Credentials

Bachelor of Arts in Criminal Justice & Corrections

Sam Houston State University, Huntsville, TX

Certifications

Certified Personal Trainer (w/ active client list)
TCOLE Training Certification

Volunteerism

Eagle Scout – Boy Scouts of America